Guide to the Peter Parker Collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
- Journals, 2.
  Peter Parker's handwritten journals including religious reflections and observations on events. The numbering of Journals 1-10 was created long ago and is retained. Journals 1-10 have been microfilmed and all journals have been digitized.
  - "Memoir" and "Journal", 1826-1827 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Peter Parker annotated on a separate slip, "The following Memoir was written during my Freshman year at A. [Amherst] Col."
  - Journal 1, 1827 November 18-1830 October 17 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Framingham, Massachusetts and Amherst College to arrival in New Haven
  - Journal 2, 1830 October 15-1831 January 25 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    New Haven, Yale College
  - Journal 3, 1831 January 28-1831 June 18 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Journal 4, 1831 June 18-1831 October 30 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    New Haven
  - Journal 5, 1831 December 25- 1834 April 13 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Journal 6, 1834 May 16-1834 October 8 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Philadelphia and travel on the Ship Morrison to Canton, China
  - Journal 7, 1834 December 23-1836 August 14 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    China
  - Journal 8, 1836 April 7-1877 June 10 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    The 1877 entry is a later addition. Most of the journal covers the period to April 22, 1855.
  - Journal 8A, 1837 June 30-1837 December 31 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    "Voyage to Japan"
  - Journal 8B, 1840 December 11-1849 June 18 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Journal 9, 1854 October 11-1876 December 11 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Includes a separate note dated 1876 January 22. Most of journal is blank.
  - Journal 10, 1856 February 24- 1880 January 31 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Most of the journal is blank. Begins with United States Legation in Macao when Parker was Commissioner.
- Sermons, addresses, and other writings, 3.
  Includes many handwritten sermons preached in Connecticut, on board the ship to China, in China, and in the U.S. and Europe (1840-1842) when promoting his missionary work. Addresses include those given by Peter Parker upon his departure to China and at the semicentennial of the Yale Theological Seminary. Papers include an essay written at Yale College, and an account of the wreck of the ship Larriston in 1853.
  - Sermons, Subseries 3.1.
    Sermons were often repeated on later dates and/or in different locations. These dates and locations are noted by Parker at the top of the sermon. Sermons are listed here under the earliest location and date.
    - Sermons, 1826-1833 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Wrentham, Mass., 1826 November 2
      - Peter Parker's "first sermon", [1826?]
        Labeled at a later date "P.P.s First Sermon." May be part of Wrentham, 1826.
      - New Haven, Conn., Plymouth, Mass. [etc.], 1832
        Five loose pages inserted in the text.
      - Booklet of sermons, Derby, Conn. [etc.], 1833 November 2
        Booklet of sermon material from which sermons were delivered also in New Haven, 1834 January 19; Plymouth, Conn., 1834 February 2; New Haven, 1834 February 9; North Haven, 1834, February 16; Cheshire, 1834 February 21; Yale College, 1834 March 1; Litchfield, 1834 March 8; Bristol, 1834 March 15; Center Church, New Haven, 1834 March 30; English Chapel, Malacca, 1835 May 31; and English Chapel, Singapore, 1835 July 12. Five inserted pages.
    - Sermons on shipboard enroute to China, 1834 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Ship Morrison, 1834 July 6
      - Ship Morrison, 1834 July 17
        "The existence of God."
      - Ship Morrison, 1834 August 20
      - Ship Morrison, Indian Ocean, 1834 September 7
        Written September 3. Preached many times through 1845.
      - Ship Morrison, Indian Ocean, 1834 September 14
        Written September 11. Includes loose item beginning "Three months have elapsed since my residence in this place."
      - Ship Morrison, Java Sea, 1834 October 5
        Written October 3. Preached several times to 1842.
      - Ship Morrison, China Sea, 1834 October 10
        Includes two inserted leaves of text (3 pages).
      - Addition to a sermon, 1834-1835
        Begins: "Three months have nearly elapsed since my residence in this place."
    - Sermons, 1835-1837 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - "Communion", 1835 April 4
      - English Chapel, Canton, 1836 July 10
        Written July 7.
      - English Chapel, Canton, 1836 July 31
        Fragments including the first page of a sermon dated June 3, 1838.
      - English Chapel, Canton, 1836 December 4
      - English Chapel, Canton, 1836 December 25
        Several blank pages at the end.
      - English Chapel, Canton, 1837 January 22
        Written January 21.
      - [English Chapel, Canton], 1837 January [22]
        Continuation of the above?
      - English Chapel, Canton [fragment of a sermon], 1837 February 26
      - "Christian's rule of duty to the heathen," English Chapel, 1837 November 17
    - Sermons, 1838-1840 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Canton, 1838 June 10
        Preached many times including in Washington, D.C.
      - Canton, New Year sermon fragment, 1839 January
      - English Chapel, Canton, 1839 Januar 6
      - English Chapel, Canton, 1840 February 9
      - Sermon beginning Tim.1:5, 1840 February 23
      - Tabernacle of New York, 1840
        Preached many places. The earliest legible date is Washington, D.C., 1841 January 24, but there is a previous date of Framingham in December.
    - Sermons, 1841-1844 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Sermon on ABCFM's need for funds, ca. 1841
        Sermon, possibly incomplete, beginning "Finally the reflection comes home to each bosom."
      - Sermon beginning Joshua 13:1, 1841 December 6
        Preached many times during the period when he was back in America. Preached in Washington, DC., May 8, 1842.
      - Sermon beginning Matth.16:20, 1842 October 16
        Written October 15.
      - On board the Paul Jones, 1843 May 28
        Sermon beginning Job 15:4.
      - Canton, 1844 September 15
        "Delivered on the occasion of the sudden deaths of Wm. A Lawrence and T. R. Waldron".
      - Canton, 1844 December 29
        Luke 13: 8, 9. Preached several times through 1862. There is a pencil note by Parker dated 1883.
    - Sermons, 1845-1875 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Canton, 1845 January 5
      - Canton, 1847 May 2
        Begins "Lord's Supper."
      - Canton, 1847 May 9
        On death of Nathan Kinsman, Esq.
      - Sermon or address labelled "1848," China
      - Canton, 1848 November 19
      - Sermon beginning Job 11: 7, 8, 9, 1875
    - Undated and incomplete sermons (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - "Origins of Idolatry", n.d.
        "As given by Paul, Rom 1:28 +"
      - Outline of a sermon beginning "Invoke the D. Blessing", n.d.
      - "A Dedicatory Prayer", n.d.
        Begins: "1 Kings 8:23."
      - Notes on the Lord's Supper, n.d.
      - Incomplete sermon missing first page(s) 1, n.d.
        Begins: "Creator had actually adopted..."
      - Incomplete sermon missing first page(s) 2, n.d.
        Begins: "some prophet, like Jeremiah..." Includes an inserted printed invitation to a meeting of the Medical Mission in China, London, July 12, 1841, and written on in pencil on both sides.
      - Miscellaneous one and two-page fragments
    - Undated and incomplete sermons (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Sermon missing first page(s) on the "Christian race" for the "prize", n.d.
      - Sermon on the sudden death of a young man
      - Sermon fragments on death, some possibly related to the above
        Reference to the death of a young minister.
  - Addresses and other writings, Subseries 3.2.
    - Addresses by Peter Parker, 1834-1842 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Farewell Address before leaving for China, 1834
      - "Address in behalf of the M. M. Society before the Citizens of Phila", 1842 January 8
      - "Meeting of the Ladies of Philadelphia...in behalf of the M. M. Soc. in China", 1842 February 8
    - Addresses by Peter Parker, 1862-1872 and n.d. (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - "Address to the orphans in the [--?] Asylum," Washington, D.C., 1862 December 24
      - Address at the Semi-Centennial of Yale Theological Seminary, 1872 May 16
      - Address on the need to send Bibles to China, Possibly 1840-1842
        Separate sheet in pencil that may be related. Parker recalled the time when he told his widowed mother that he wanted to go to China as a missionary.
    - Manuscripts, dated, 1830-1879 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - "A study of the sciences necessary to professional excellence", 1830?
      - "Practical utility of the sciences of Chemistry, & Nat. Philosophy to the professional man", 1830 April 2
      - Manuscript on the wreck of the steamer Larriston on the way from Shanghai to Canton, 1853
      - Manuscript beginning "O Thou Supreme Architect," Washington, D.C., 1860 May 19
        A blessing on his new house. Signed by Peter Parker and Harriet Colby Webster Parker.
      - Manuscript on the occasion of laying the cornerstone of his house, Washington, D.C., 1860 May 19
        Contains autobiographical material.
      - Envelope: Peter Parker, "Copies of Papers Sealed up in a Glass Bottle...", 1860 May 19
        Envelope only. The bottle was placed in a corner of the foundation of Parker's house in Washington, D.C. and probably included originals of the above two items.
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts, dated, 1834-1879 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Notes on religious subjects, 1834-1879
        Note on death by Parker, Washington, D.C., February 17, 1879; note by Parker on "Sanctification," December 16, 1861; "Sacraments" by Parker, Canton, November 15, 1834.
      - List by Parker of the Governors of Macao, 1829-1857, ca. 1857
    - Manuscripts, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Comments on various literary figures beginning with George Crabbe, n.d.
      - Timeline and manuscript on the history of China
        Timeline is a separate sheet.
      - Manuscript in Chinese, n.d.
    - Manuscripts, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - "Antient Tablets", n.d.
        On Chinese artifacts and history. Fragile condition.
      - Note beginning "Caesar Commentarius", n.d.
      - Two brief pencil notes, n.d.
    - Miscellaneous notes by Peter Parker and others (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Printed list of missionaries sent to China, ca. 1849
      - Brief notes from travel to London and Paris, [1841?]
      - Memento with pink ribbon signed by [?] Cushing, n.d.
        Contains ethnographic images of birds.
      - Dates related to Parker's service as Commissioner to China and list of memberships in organizations, ca. 1880
      - List of "invited guests", 1864 February 27
      - Notes on reading, n.d.
      - Fragment on eternity, n.d.
      - Religious notes on a paper with the address of F. Seward, n.d.
      - Notes in Arabic, n.d.
- Medical reports and ledgers, 4.
  - Reports of the Ophthalmic Hospital at Canton, Subseries 4.1.
    These reports contain case accounts of individual patients, in particular a number of patients painted by Lam Qua. See the typescripts in Box 7 which transcribe reports 1-11.
    - Reports of the Ophthalmic Hospital at Canton, 1-4, 1836 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - First Quarterly Report, 1835 November 4 - 1836 November 4
      - Second Quarterly Report, 1836 February 4 - 1836 May 4
      - Third Quarterly Report, 1836 May 4 - 1836 August 4
      - Fourth Quarterly Report, 1836 August 4 - 1836 November 4
    - Reports of the Ophthalmic Hospital at Canton, 5-8, 1837-1838 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Fifth Quarterly Report, 1836 November 4-1837 February 4
      - Sixth Quarterly Report, 1837 February 4 - 1837 May 4
      - Seventh Quarterly Report, 1837 December 31
      - Eighth Quarterly Report, 1838 January 1 - 1838 June 30
  - Ledgers, Subseries 4.2.
    - Canton Hospital ledger, 1851-1853 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Name of patient, age, birthplace, and occupation in Chinese, medical problems in English. One line per entry. Entries 40770-47129. Inserted is a drawing of a Chinese child with a growth on his face.
    - Canton Hospital ledger, 1853-1855 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Continuation of above. Entries 47130-53049. Inserted as a loose sheet is a two-page document in Chinese on red paper.
    - Medical practice ledger, 1845-1855 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      In English. Parker's private medical practice including fees.
    - Financial ledger, 1861-1885 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Parker's expenditures
    - Bound volume of typescripts of the Canton Hospital Reports and of other publications on medical missionaries, 1835-1843 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Bound volume (acc. 27408), donated by the widow of William Warder Cadbury, M.D. (1877-1959), who arrived in Canton 1909 where he taught at Canton Christian College and practiced at Canton Hospital. It contains typescripts of the Canton Hospital Reports, 1-11 (1835-1840); Extracts from William Lockhart, "Medical Missionary in China"; Medical Missionary Society Regulations and Resolutions, 1838; First Report of the Medical Missionary Society's Hospital at Macao; First Annual Report of the Medical Missionary Society, 1838; Inquest on a Dead Patient; Report of the Medical Missionary Society, 1839; Second report of the Medical Missionary Society of China, 1840; Report of the Medical Missionary Society, 1843.
    - Bound volume of typescripts of primary printed sources related to medical missionaries in China and Peter Parker, 1836-1888 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Includes an article by Parker. In the back of the volume are handwritten notes on urinary calculi. On spine: "Memorabilia Concerning Dr. Peter Parker." See urinary calculi, Box 11. Volume has bookplate of Samuel C. Harvey. This volume has not yet been photographed.
- Miscellaneous, 5.
  - Dinner at Cutler's Hall, Sheffield, 1880 September 2 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Includes invitation from William Chesterman, the Master cutler-elect; menu; order of seating; and place card for Peter Parker.
  - Congressional Temperance Society, 1833 February 14 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Signed agreement to form a Congressional Temperance Society (1833) and words to "Ye Old Granite State," a temperance song.
  - Letter from the Ambassador from France to Brazil, Washington, D.C., to Rothschild, Banker in London, 1821 March 8 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    In French. No clear relation to Parker.
  - Printed hymn composed for a sermon by Peter Parker in Macao on the death of Mary Sword, 1845 July 24 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Printed invitation to Mrs. H. Lindsly to attend a ball in honor of Lord and Lady Napier, 1859 February 17 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Mrs. Lindsly was Mrs. Parker's sister.
  - List of paintings, statuary, and busts (Box 8, Folder 6)
    These are likely the collection of the Smithsonian Institution. See General William T. Sherman to Peter Parker, February 13, 1873, Box 1, folder 20.
  - New Year's greetings to Peter Parker from "a constant friend" (Box 8, Folder 7)
    On a laced sheet with tiny knitted gloves attached.
  - Program of selections from Roberts' and Wright's Glee Choir (Box 8, Folder 8)
    From England.
  - Poems, 1829-1854 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Five handwritten poems. One is "To Mrs. Parker on her Birth Day." Another, possibly written by Parker, is "A Mother's Farewell."
  - Prescriptions, 1850-1855 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Three items by or related to Parker.
  - Sketch book, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 11)
    Very preliminary sketches of scenery with handwriting that is not Parker's.
  - Testimony to Christianity, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 12)
    Printed sheet: "Testimony to the truth of Christianity, given by Kiying late governor-general of Canton..." in English and Chinese; envelope on which is written "Canton Hospital/ Testimony to Christianity J.C. Stewart to P.P." See J. C. Stewart correspondence in Box 1, folder 20.
  - Dr. J. C. Thomson, "Medical Missionary Society in China", 1888 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Printed columns pasted into a sewn pamphlet. The pamphlet recounts the history of the Society including Peter Parker's role.
  - "Remarks of the Rev. Dr. B. Sunderland at the obsequies of Dr. Peter Parker," copy 1, 1888 January 13 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - "Remarks of the Rev. Dr. B. Sunderland at the obsequies of Dr. Peter Parker," copy 2, 1888 January 13 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Notes between Carl Lohmann and Milton Winternitz about a Chinese manuscript, 1935 April (Box 8, Folder 15)
    Carl Lohmann was secretary of Yale University, and Milton Winternitz was the Dean of Yale School of Medicine. These two notes were found with the additional photographs from Canton Hospital and refer to gift materials from William Warder Cadbury related to Peter Parker or Canton Hospital. The manuscript was a druggist's request for payment of a bill.
  - Peter Parker's Bible in Greek, 2 vols., 1831-1832 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    Latin titles are Vetus Testamentum and Novum Testamentum. Published in Glasgow. Peter Parker's China bookplate. This Bible has not been photographed.
- Photographs, 6.
  Includes photographs of the oil paintings by Lam Qua, photographs of the staff of Canton Hospital after the time of Peter Parker, and lantern slides of Canton Hospital and of patients with large tumors.
  - Photographs of Lam Qua paintings taken under the direction of Moses C. White, 1880-1900 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Parker gave the portraits to Yale through Moses C. White, professor of pathology, who had been a missionary to China.
  - Moses C. White's notes on paintings and loose photographs of paintings, 1880-1900 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    The notes match cases to the Canton Hospital ledgers (Box 6, Folders 3 and 4), provide details of several of the cases, and give references to Parker's published reports.
  - Photograph Album of Canton Hospital, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Donated by the Mrs. William Warder Cadbury, 1966. Dr. Cadbury arrived in China in 1909, taught at the Canton Christian College, and practiced at the Canton Hospital. A number of snapshots are identified in Chinese. There are three loose photographs.
  - Additional Canton Hospital photographs, 1924, 1947, and n.d. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Lantern slides (unprocessed), early 20th century? (Box 10)
    Donated by Mrs. William Warder Cadbury, 1966. Images are of the hospital, staff, and of Chinese patients with huge tumors of the type that Peter Parker treated. These slides have not been processed or photographed.
- Urinary calculi, 7.
  - Urinary calucli from Peter Parker's patients, 1842-1855 (Box 11)
    Includes the actual calculi, 31 photographs, and a drawing of the calculi probably created at Yale. Some of the photographs are matched to Canton Hospital case numbers. See Series 4, Box 7, folder 2 for notes and drawings of some of the calculi. The calculi have not been photographed.